Finding Aid for Alexander G. Ruthven speeches, articles, pamphlets, reprints, 1929-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alexander G. Ruthven speeches, articles, pamphlets, reprints 1929-1944
Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-
46 items in 1 box
[745] DA 2; R976; S742
President of the University of Michigan, commencement speeches, addresses, articles and miscellaneous publications on academic and administrative issue at the University of Michigan and higher education generally.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a variety of sources.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Alexander G. Ruthven was born April 1, 1882 in Hull, Iowa. He received his BS degree in 1903 from Morningside College and his Ph.D. in Zoology from the University of Michigan. As a zoologist, Ruthven's major interest was in reptiles and amphibians - snakes, lizards turtles, frogs, etc. He wrote extensively in his disciple and also directed various scientific expeditions in North, South and Central America. Also, before assuming the presidency, Ruthven was chief field naturalist with the Michigan Geological and Biological Survey (1908-1912).
Ruthven's entire career was spent at the University of Michigan where he was successively instructor of zoology and curator of the Museum of Zoology (1906-1911); assistant professor and curator of the Museum of Zoology (1911-1913); assistant professor and director of the Museum of Zoology (1913-1915); profess and director of the Museum of Zoology (1915-1929); director of University Museums (1922-1936); chairman of the department of zoology and director of the Zoological Laboratories (1927-1929); and dean of administration (1928-1929). Upon President Little's resignation, Ruthven was named to a committee of three to administer the affairs of the University. With administrative skills demonstrated in this position, Ruthven in October 1929 was selected by the regents as president of the University of Michigan. He served in this position until 1951 when Harlan Hatcher assumed office.
Upon assuming office as president, Ruthven worked to reform the administrative structure of the university. He believed that the university must distribute authority and responsibility among the many units and officers which make up the total structure. Early on he selected two vice-presidents, one in charge of business affairs and the other in charge of educational investigations. He also appointed a director of plant extension, and some time later, a vice-president in charge of university relations outside the campus. In 1944, the university's administrative structure included a provost, two vice-presidents, and a secretary. Deans and directors of schools, colleges, and other educational units were given authority commensurate with their responsibilities. Usually, advisory or executive committees were set up to aid unit heads with their duties.
During Ruthven's tenure, the School of Music was formally affiliated and integration with the university. In 1941, the School of Public Health was established; and in 1951, the School of Social Work was established. Other important developments during his tenure were the creation of an Institute of Public Administration and the reorganization of the School of Forestry as the School of Natural Resources.
Ruthven died January 19, 1971.
The Ruthven speeches and publications collections consists of commencement speeches, addresses, articles and miscellaneous publications on academic and administrative issue at the University of Michigan and higher education generally.
Subjects:
Baccalaureate addresses.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-; University of Michigan--Presidents--Biography.; University of Michigan--History.
- Speeches, articles, pamphlets, reprints
  - "Some Problems of the University". University of Michigan Official Publications,Vol. XXXI, no. 27. November 16, 1929. (Box 1)
  - "Predicts Decline in Athletic Interest." Michigan Alumnus, November 29, 1930.
  - "The Good Alumnus". Baccalaureate Address, 1930.
  - "Pride and Prejudice". An address given at the Second Baptist Church, Ann Arbor, October 18, 1931.
  - "A Brief for the Large University".University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol .XXXII, no. 37. January 10, 1931.
  - "University President on College Temptations". Michigan Christian-Advocate, October 29, 1931.
  - "Administration at Michigan", 1931
  - "Evils of our Colleges", 1931
  - "The Michigan Plan", 1931
  - "Our System of Higher Education", 1931
  - "Ethical and Religious Values in Education". Religious Education, April, 1932.
  - "The Super-University"/"The University Housing Program". University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol. XXXIII, no. 37.
  - "Parental Training". 1932.
  - "Problems and Progress at the University of Michigan" University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol. XXXIV, no. 47.
  - "Religious Instruction at the University of Michigan", November 16, 1933
  - "Preparation of the Budget", 1934
  - "Discipline as a Factor in Social Integration". University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol. XXXVI, no. 15. August 22, 1934.
  - "Modern Trends in Professional Education". 1934
  - "Problems and Progress at the University of Michigan". University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol. 35, no. 16, Jan 1934.
  - "Experiencing Education". Official publication, Bureau of Alumni Relations, University of Michigan, January 27, 1934.
  - "Some Thoughts on Retiring Ages", 1934
  - "Code for Professors" 1935.
  - "An Eternal Triangle". Baccalaureate address, June 1935
  - Commencement address, June 1936
  - "Academic Freedom", 1937
  - "Cultivation or Confusion", Commencement address., 1937
  - "Leadership or Regimentation in Higher Education", 1937
  - "Uses of Publicity as seen by a University President", 1939
  - "Some Remarks on the Organization of Research in the Universities", 1938
  - "Education and Service". Commencement address, June 18, 1938
  - "Common Sense of Religion", 1939
  - Excerpts from the president's report, 1939-1940
  - "A Decade of University History". University of Michigan Official Publications, Vol. 41, no.68. February 21, 1940.
  - "Never to Grow Old". Commencement address., 1940
  - "Balancing the Curricula".The Classical Journal, Vol. XXXV, no. 7. April 1940.
  - "The University of Michigan and National Defense". Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review, April 26, 1941.
  - "Our Moral Heritage". 1941.
  - "Universities in Wartime".The Nation's Schools, Vol. 31, no. 1. January 1943.
  - "A Liberal Arts College in the Modern World", 1940
  - "A Wartime Address to the Alumni". Vol. 43, no. 133.
  - "The Armor of Honest Thought" Commencement address, 1942
  - "Creative Imagination in Wartime". 1943. Commencement address, University of New Mexico, February 25, 1944
  - "The Need for Higher Education to Study its Program", 1945
  - "Now that commencement is here".
  - Unlisted clippings, 2 folders